export const SOCIALSTUDIESA2015 = [

{
id: "question1",
question: "1. An individual’s self-concept includes his/her",
A: "conventions",
B: "customs",
C: "decrees",
D: "perceptions",
answer: "D. perceptions",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question: "2. The following options ate conditions that false identity can create except",
A: "hatred and mistrust",
B: "rejection of such people",
C: "social vices",
D: "urbanization",
answer: "D. urbanization",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question: "3. One factor that can inhibit the development of an individual’s capabilities is",
A: "awareness of one’s capabilities",
B: "education and training",
C: "inferiority complex",
D: "self-determination",
answer: "C. inferiority complex",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question: "4. Adolescent reproductive health risks include",
A: "cholera",
B: "dysentery",
C: "HIV and AIDS",
D: "D. jaundice",
answer: "C. HIV and AIDS",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question: "5. In the traditional society, the ceremony performed to mark the transition from childhood to adulthood is",
A: "adolescent rite",
B: "fertility rite",
C: "initiation rite",
D: "puberty rite",
answer: "C. initiation rite",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question: "6. Adolescent chastity is beneficial because it",
A: "enhances interpersonal relations",
B: "contributes to population growth",
C: "leads to the creation of employment",
D: "produces responsible parents",
answer: "D. produces responsible parents",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question: "7. Which of the following ceremonies does not involve a rite of passage?",
A: "Birth",
B: "Death",
C: "Festival",
D: "Puberty",
answer: "C. Festival",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question: "8. It is necessary to preserve our cultural heritage because it",
A: "ensures continuity of society",
B: "makes culture unique",
C: "promotes national reconciliation",
D: "creates more employment",
answer: "B. makes culture unique",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question: "9. The effect of childlessness in marriage can be overcome when there is",
A: "abundant financial resources",
B: "genuine love and commitment",
C: "no external family interference",
D: "D. periodic personal diagnosis",
answer: "B. genuine love and commitment",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question: "10. The residential arrangement in which the husband and wife live separately in the respective houses of their parents is",
A: "duolocal",
B: "matrilocal",
C: "neolocal",
D: "patrilocal",
answer: "A. duolocal",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question11",
question: "11. In a nuclear family, the wife is considered a breadwinner because she",
A: "ensures the moral upbringing of the children",
B: "protect the image of the family",
C: "supplements the income of family",
D: "support the extended family",
answer: "C. supplements the income of family",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question: "12. An essential role of the family as a social institution is that, it",
A: "ensures maintenance of culture heritage",
B: "ensures progress and social stability",
C: "provides affection, belongingness and security",
D: "provides opportunity for inheritance",
answer: "C. provides affection, belongingness and security",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question: "13. Parent-child conflict is minimized when parents",
A: "listen to the views of the child",
B: "report the child to school authority",
C: "report the child to religious authority",
D: "reprimand the child instantly",
answer: "A. listen to the views of the child",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question14",
question: "14. The process by which the individual learns the norms, values and patterns of behavior which enable him/her to fit into society is known as",
A: "acculturation",
B: "assimilation",
C: "indoctrination",
D: "socialization",
answer: "D. socialization",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question15",
question: "15. Good interpersonal relations is best achieved through",
A: "dialogue",
B: "generosity",
C: "submissiveness",
D: "tolerance",
answer: "D. tolerance",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question16",
question: "16. One effect of global warning on the physical environment is the",
A: "burning of fossil fuel",
B: "increase in industrial pollution",
C: "increase in volcanic eruptions",
D: "rise in sea levels and flooding",
answer: "D. rise in sea levels and flooding",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question: "17. Provision of environmental education helps us to",
A: "keep our environment clean",
B: "realize the implications of large population",
C: "understand environmental pollution",
D: "understand ways of fighting fire",
answer: "A. keep our environment clean",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question: "18. Which of the following factors is an impediment to rapid social change in Ghana?",
A: "culture",
B: "education",
C: "technology",
D: "urbanization",
answer: "A. culture",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question: "19. In the Ghanaian society, the value of an individual’s education is measured by his/her",
A: "ability to speak in public",
B: "contribution to development",
C: "level of intelligence",
D: "stock of wealth",
answer: "B. contribution to development",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question: "20. Political independence demands that",
A: "citizens adopt laissez-faire attitude to work",
B: "citizens work hard to salvage the economy",
C: "the government seeks donor support always",
D: "the nation serves all ties with her colonial master",
answer: "D. the nation serves all ties with her colonial master",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question: "21. A show of superiority of one ethnic group over the other in Ghana is dangerous because it",
A: "brings about religious intolerance",
B: "creates chieftaincy disputes",
C: "generate indiscipline in the media",
D: "threatens peace and national cohesion",
answer: "D. threatens peace and national cohesion",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question: "22. Which of the following leadership styles involves irregular and strict supervision of followers?",
A: "Autocratic",
B: "Democratic",
C: "Laissez-faire",
D: "D. Paternalistic",
answer: "A. Autocratic",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question: "23. A member of a group who accepts to be led and guided with rules and regulations is?",
A: "a follower",
B: "a leader",
C: "an association",
D: "an overseer",
answer: "A. a follower",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question: "24. A leader performs the following roles except",
A: "arresting deviants",
B: "decision making",
C: "enforcing rules",
D: "strategic planning",
answer: "A. arresting deviants",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question: "25. Which of the following options is a feature of rule of law?",
A: "enjoyment of fundamental human rights",
B: "establishment of courts and tribunals",
C: "institution of chieftaincy",
D: "representation in parliament",
answer: "A. enjoyment of fundamental human rights",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question26",
question: "26. The practice of democracy promotes unity and development mainly because of the",
A: "existence of independent judiciary",
B: "involvement of the people in decision making",
C: "provision of social amenities",
D: "D. regular inflow of foreign aid",
answer: "B. involvement of the people in decision making",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question: "27. Which of the following principals of democracy places emphasis on equality of all persons?",
A: "Checks and balances",
B: "Free press",
C: "Rule of law",
D: "separation of powers",
answer: "B. Free press",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question: "28. Services that individuals are obliged to perform to the state are",
A: "conventions",
B: "occupations",
C: "responsibilities",
D: "rights",
answer: "C. responsibilities",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question: "29. Fundamental human rights are protected by governments because they are",
A: "democratic in nature",
B: "inherent in the very nature of man",
C: "pronounced by the Chief Justice",
D: "provided by the president of the country",
answer: "B. inherent in the very nature of man",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question30",
question: "30. One benefit of being a member of an international organization is",
A: "achievement of autonomy",
B: "economic development",
C: "promotion of neo-colonialism",
D: "D. reduction in population",
answer: "B. economic development",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question: "31. The avenue through which the New Partnership for Africa’s Development (NEPAD) fosters stability economic growth and development is the",
A: "institution of peer review mechanism",
B: "organization of African games",
C: "organization of trade fairs",
D: "setting up of African Investment Bank",
answer: "A. institution of peer review mechanism",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question: "32. Guidance and counseling services provided the youth the economy prepare them to",
A: "be individualistic",
B: "make informed choices",
C: "join political parties",
D: "organize social clubs",
answer: "B. make informed choices",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question: "33. To be able to transform and modernize the economy, the youth need",
A: "manage certificates",
B: "requisite skills",
C: "to acquire leadership skills",
D: "to belong to pressure groups",
answer: "B. consulting the internet for vacancies",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question34",
question: "34. The use of appropriate technology in developing countries results in",
A: "decrease in production",
B: "depletion of the ozone layer",
C: "destruction of natural resources",
D: "high standard of living",
answer: "D. high standard of living",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question35",
question: "35. The ultimate goal for making science a compulsory subject in Ghanaian school is to",
A: "encourage interest in the subject",
B: "facilitate the process of technological development",
C: "help establish more research institutions",
D: "produce more artisans for the local industries",
answer: "A. encourage interest in the subject",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question: "36. The skills of workers and management that a country has constitute the",
A: "capital resources",
B: "human resource",
C: "managerial resource",
D: "D. natural resource",
answer: "B. human resource",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question: "37. The most essential factors that contribute to effective utilization of natural resources are",
A: "capital and technical know-how",
B: "planning and budgeting",
C: "research and exploration",
D: "D. vision and commitment",
answer: "A. capital and technical know-how",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question: "38. A positive change in attitudes and values which help in improving the standard of living of the people in an area is referred to as",
A: "community development",
B: "cultural assimilation",
C: "cultural improvement",
D: "socio-cultural practice",
answer: "A. community development",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question39",
question: "39. An individual can contribute to the development of his or her community through the following ways except",
A: "felling trees for charcoal production",
B: "offering technical advice",
C: "participation in communal labour",
D: "participation in decision making",
answer: "A. felling trees for charcoal production",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question: "40. Countries industrialize mainly because they want to",
A: "encourage individuals to own business",
B: "improve the standard of living of the people",
C: "make the private sector the engine of growth",
D: "seek foreign technical assistance",
answer: "B. improve the standard of living of the people",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question41",
question: "41. National development can be explained as",
A: "finding white collar job for the people",
B: "making resources available to the people",
C: "opportunities available to expand the economy of the nation",
D: "progress made to improve the standard and quality of life",
answer: "D. progress made to improve the standard and quality of life",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question42",
question: "42. Which of the following measures should Ghana adopt to attain food sufficiency?",
A: "dependence on rain-fed agriculture",
B: "importation of food from abroad",
C: "intensification of mechanised farming",
D: "reliance on traditional methods of farming",
answer: "C. intensification of mechanised farming",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question: "43. When a country’s development is uninterrupted over a long period of time it is described as",
A: "flexible",
B: "reversible",
C: "sustainable",
D: "vulnerable",
answer: "C. sustainable",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question: "44. It is important to plan for the future for the following reasons except",
A: "maintaining one’s loyalty to a political party",
B: "maintaining one’s standard of living",
C: "mobilizing capital for business",
D: "preventing borrowing to meet one’s need",
answer: "A. maintaining one's loyalty to a political party",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question: "45. Inadequate supply of fertilizer to farmers can result in",
A: "migration of farmers",
B: "poor crop harvest",
C: "post-harvest losses",
D: "spread of pest",
answer: "B. poor crop harvest",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question46",
question: "46. Rapid population growth can lead to",
A: "high dependency burden",
B: "high standard of living",
C: "low employment rate",
D: "low mortality rate",
answer: "A. high dependency burden",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question: "47. Spacing child bearing",
A: "encourages rivalry among siblings",
B: "increases medical cost of families",
C: "reduces a country’s labour force",
D: "safeguards the life of the child",
answer: "D. safeguards the life of the child",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question: "48. Poor attitude to work leads to",
A: "high financial losses",
B: "low prices of goods",
C: "low technology",
D: "poor communication",
answer: "A. high financial losses",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question: "49. One advantage of Joint Stock Company is that, its shareholders have",
A: "company code",
B: "large capital",
C: "limited liability",
D: "secure tenure",
answer: "C. limited liability",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question50",
question: "50. The democratic method of selecting representatives is mostly employed in",
A: "Co-operative society",
B: "Partnership",
C: "Private Joint Stock Company",
D: "Public Corporations",
answer: "A. Co-operative society",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]